<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN" "../DocBook/docbook-5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd">
<article>
	<info>
		<title>SPARK-PL: Introduction</title>
		<author>
			<personname>Alexey Solovyev</personname>
		</author>
		<abstract>
			<para>
				All basic elements of SPARK-PL are introduced.
			</para>
		</abstract>
	</info>
	
	<sect1>
		<title>Introduction to SPARK-PL</title>
		<para>
			SPARK-PL (SPARK Programming Language) is a special language
			for implementing SPARK models.
			
			Its syntax is derived primary from Logo programming language (influenced by NetLogo) and Java programming language. 
			All models written in SPARK-PL are translated into Java source code first, and 
			then a Java compiler is used to produce the machine code which can be executed by the SPARK simulation engine. 
			SPARK-PL has static type system which helps to eliminate many programmers’ errors concerning an incorrect 
			use of variables of incompatible types. Type inference mechanism of SPARK-PL makes it easy to implement 
			models in the way similar to languages with a dynamic type system. 
			With type inference, it is not required to provide an explicit type for every new variable. 
			The translator is capable to find the correct type in many cases automatically by looking at the expressions 
			where variables are used. 
		</para>
		<para>
			Every SPARK model written in
			SPARK-PL consists of several SPARK-PL source code files.
			These files constitute a SPARK-PL project. SPARK-PL projects
			are managed by a special program called the SPARK-PL Project Manager.
			<figure>
				<title>The SPARK-PL Project Manager</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata align="left" width="6in" format="PNG"
							fileref="images/ProjectManager.png" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
			The list on the left shows all files in a project. 
			New files can be added by clicking 'Add' button which brings in 
			an open file dialog. Button '…' allows to choose another 
			model directory. Projects can be saved via 'File' menu 'Save project...' command. 
			The button 'Translate' is used for translation a SPARK-PL source code into 
			a Java source code which then can be compiled by clicking the 'Compile' button. 
			'Run in SPARK button' runs the compiled model in SPARK. 
			'Start' button is a shortcut for all three main actions: translate, compile, and then
			run in SPARK.
		</para>
		<para>
			Step by step instruction on creating new SPARK-PL projects.
			First, create SPARK-PL source code files in any plain text
			editor. Save them in a folder which will be a main project
			folder. Click '...' button in the project manager and
			select the project folder. Add source code files into the
			manager using 'Add' button. Save the project description
			file by selecting 'Save project...' item from the 'File' menu.
			The project description file is a simple xml file which
			contains the information about all files inside the project.
			Note that this file should be in the same project folder as
			source code files. Click 'Translate' button. If any error occurs,
			correct it and click 'Translate' again. After elimination of
			all translation errors and after successful translation,
			click 'Compile' button. Again, there could be some compilation
			errors which also can be corrected. After a successful compilation
			process, click 'Run in SPARK' button to run a model in SPARK.
			It is always possible to use only 'Start' button instead of
			three other buttons. But for the first time, it is better to
			use 'Translate', 'Compile', 'Run in SPARK' sequence in order
			to simplify the error correction process.
		</para>
		<para>
			To open an existing project description file, select 'Open project...'
			item from the 'File' menu. Also, 10 most recently open projects are
			available directly in the 'File' menu. If you later add some
			new files to an existing project, do not forget to save
			the description file again using 'Save project...' command.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	
	
	<sect1>
		<title>Alphabet of SPARK-PL</title>
		<para>
			Valid symbols in SPARK-PL source code files are all Latin
			letters, digits, period '.', colon ':', comma ',', square
			brackets '[' and ']', parentheses '(' and ')',  
			and symbols '_', '^', '+', '-', '*', '/', '=', '%', '&lt;', '&gt;',
			'!'. Semicolon ';' denotes a comment: everything after a semicolon
			is not parsed by a SPARK-PL translator and treated as a
			comment. 
		</para>
		<para>
			Type names, variable names, command names are identifiers.
			Identifiers start from a letter and can include any letters,
			digits, and dashes '-'. All identifiers are case sensitive.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
; A comment

; A variable named 'some-variable' is declared and
; initialized
var some-variable = 20.2

; This is a different variable
var Some-variable = 10.123e-10

; This is the third variable
var SomeVariable = "string"
</programlisting>
			SPARK-PL has many similarities with languages from the Logo family.
			That's why identifiers can include the dash symbol. Because of
			that, an attention should be paid to distinguish dash and minus.
			The rule is simple: minus should be always separated by spaces.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	
	<sect1>
		<title>Types and variables</title>
		<para>
			All SPARK-PL source files should begin with one of the following declarations
<programlisting language="SPARK">
class class-name : parent-type
agent agent-name : parent-type
model model-name : parent-type
</programlisting>
			In fact, everything in SPARK-PL is encapsulated inside classes
			(or types). 'agent' and 'model' are special types which will
			be described later. All types has a name and a parent type
			from which they inherit functions and properties. Usual classes
			and models are not required to have a parent type. For agents
			a parent type is required (see the agent tutorial for details).
			After a new type declaration on the first line of a source file,
			a type definition follows. Everything written after a type
			declaration is considered to be included inside that type.
			But it is also possible to include several type declarations
			in one source file. To do so, just start a new type
			declaration in any place of a source file. Then everything
			before that new declaration belongs to the previously declared
			type, and everything after will belong to a new type.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
class Class1

; definition of Class1

; Declare a new type which has the previous
; type as its parent type
class Class2 : Class1

; definition of Class2

; One more type
class Class3

; definition of Class3
</programlisting>
			Note that each SPARK model must contain one and only one
			model class.
		</para>
		<para>
			Several types (classes) can be defined in one file, but it is also
			possible to split a declaration of one class into several files.
			It can be achieved by adding the 'partial' keyword before declaring
			the corresponding type:
<programlisting language="SPARK">
; Inside file1
partial class Class1

; definition of Class1

partial class Class2 : Class1

; definition of Class2

; Inside file2
partial class Class1

; The parent type should be the same for all partial declarations
partial class Class2 : Class1
</programlisting>
			Models, agents, and classes can be declared with the 'partial' keyword.
			It is always recommended to completely declare one type in one file
			unless there is a definite benefit of using partial declarations.
			One possible usage of partial declarations is to split the main
			model into two files: one file contains all model functions, another file contains
			all global variables and parameters. In this way it is simpler to add
			new parameters and to manage global variables.
		</para>
		<para>
				SPARK-PL consists of commands, control structures and declarations. 
				There are many globally defined commands, for example
				'ask', 'create', 'random', 'random-vector', etc.
				Commands defined inside classes are called methods. 
				Variables defined inside classes are called fields. 
				Declaration of a variable looks like the following
<programlisting language="SPARK">
var x : number
</programlisting>
				Here 'var' is a keyword, 'number' is a type. 
				A type name can be omitted. In that case a variable is treated 
				as a variable of unknown type. It is possible that the type
				will be determined automatically later. 
				For example, if we have a code
<programlisting language="SPARK">
var x
x = 2
</programlisting>
				Then after the assignment the type of x becomes 'number'. 
				On the other hand, there are many situations 
				when the type cannot be determined automatically 
				(especially in the current implementation of 
				the type inferring algorithm). Because of this, 
				it is recommended to explicitly specify types of all fields 
				and method arguments. It is possible to initialize 
				a variable during its declaration
<programlisting language="SPARK">
var x = 3
</programlisting>
				There is another keyword 'global' for declaring global
				variables. These variables are available not only in
				the type where they are declared but also in other types.
				And you only need to know their name to access them in any
				part of a code. Global variables can be declared inside any class or agent,
				but it is a good practice to declare global variables only inside model types.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
model Model

; x will be available in any part of a code
global x = 30
</programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>				
				Methods are declared as follows
<programlisting language="SPARK">
to method-name [arg1:type arg2:type] : method-type
; Method's body
end
</programlisting>
				If there are no arguments in a method then you
				may omit square brackets for arguments.
				All explicit type declarations are unnecessary. A return
				type of a method, 'method-type', can also be omitted.
				In that case a method will have no return type. If a method
				has a return type then its last command should be
				'return some-value' where 'some-value' has the same
				type as method's type.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
to add-numbers [a b] : number
[
	var result = a + b
	return result
]
</programlisting> 
			</para>
			<para>
				There is one very important rule associated with SPARK-PL
				commands and methods. If a command returns some value then 
				it is required to use parentheses for all its arguments which
				have complex structure (not a single identifier or a constant). 
				For commands without return value
				it is not required. It seems to be confusing and not useful
				but it helps to reduce the number of parentheses in
				a program. In any case, it is always better to enter additional
				parentheses in order to avoid unexpected compile errors.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
agent SomeAgent : SpaceAgent

to some-method
	var v : vector
	; The next command is translated as
	; var x = (random 100) + 20
	; because 'random' returns a value so all its arguments
	; must be inside parentheses of have a simple structure
	var x = random 100 + 20
	
	v.x = x
	x = random (100 + x)
	v.y = y
	
	; The next command is translated as
	; move-to (v + (x * v))
	; because 'move-to' does not return any value.
	move-to v + x * v	
end
</programlisting>
			</para>
			<para>
				Every SPARK model should have the main model class. This class
				is declared using 'model' keyword. The minimal working
				SPARK model written in SPARK-PL may look as follows
<programlisting language="SPARK">
model Model

space StandardSpace -10 10 -10 10 true true
</programlisting>
				Right now you may ignore the second line where the model space
				is declared. You will learn about spaces later. Now you
				only need to know that it is a requirement to declare
				a space.
			</para>
			<para>
				This minimal model is not useful. To make it more interesting,
				several methods should be added. The first method to add
				is the 'setup' method. This method is called every time
				when a model is initialized. Note that if you have an explicit
				initialization for a global variable then this initialization
				will be processed each time the 'setup' method is called. 
				There are other two special
				methods: 'begin-step' and 'end-step' inside the main model class.
				The method 'begin-step' is called before each simulation
				step, the method 'end-step' is called after each simulation
				step. The precise declarations of these methods are the following
<programlisting language="SPARK">
model Model

space StandardSpace -10 10 -10 10 true true

to setup
	; Initialize a model
end

to begin-step [tick] : boolean
end

to end-step [tick] : boolean
end
</programlisting>
			The return type 'boolean' is not required for 
			'end-step' and 'begin-step' methods. It will be added automatically.
			Moreover, you don't need to write a return command. By default,
			these methods return false value. If any of these methods
			returns true value, then a simulation will be stopped.
			So these methods can control a simulation process and stop
			it if necessary.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
to begin-step [tick]
	; Automatically stops a simulation after 1000 steps
	if tick >= 1000
		[ return true ]
end
</programlisting>
			Also, it is possible to omit 'tick' argument for these two
			methods. This argument counts the number of steps passed
			from the beginning of a simulation process. If you don't
			supply this argument, then it will be automatically created. 
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	
	<sect1>
		<title>SPARK-PL basic commands</title>
		<para>
			The most important command which controls a program
			flow is 'if'. It has two arguments: a boolean value
			and a special argument representing a block of a code.
			This block of code is executed only if the argument is
			true.
			An example clarifies everything.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
var a = 3

if a > 2
[
	do-something
]
</programlisting>
			There is a modification of this command 'ifelse' which
			has an additional code block argument which is executed
			when the condition (the first argument) is false.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
ifelse a > 2
[
	do-something
]
[
	do-something-else
]
</programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			The command 'repeat' repeats a block of commands
			several times.
<programlisting language = "SPARK">
var n = 100

; Do something 100 times
repeat n
[
	do-something
]
</programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			The command 'while' repeatedly executes a given block of
			commands meanwhile a condition is true.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
var n = 100

while n > 0
[
	do-something
	n = n - 1
]
</programlisting> 
		</para>
		<para>
			There is a very special command (a keyword) 'for' which
			is used for iterating some value. It has the following
			syntax
<programlisting language="SPARK">
for var-name = first-value : step : last-value
[
	do-something
	; var-name is available here as a numerical variable
]
</programlisting>
			Here 'var-name' is any identifier. The only condition is
			that there is no local variable with the same name.
			'first-value', 'step', and 'last-value' are numbers (or
			numerical expressions). 'first-value' specifies the initial
			value of the variable 'var-name'. 'step' specifies an increment of that
			variable. 'last-value' specify when to stop the iterations.
			Iterations will stop when the value of 'var-name' becomes
			greater than 'last-value'. 'step' is an optional argument
			and can be omitted.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
; Prints out numbers from 1 to 100
for i = 1 : 100
[
	print i
]
</programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			If a user method in SPARK-PL has return type then the command
			'return value' can be used to exit from this method at any point.
			For methods without return type this command is not available
			because it always requires an argument. In that case,
			the command 'exit' can be used. 
		</para>
		<para>
			There are two commands which control the iterative processes
			'while', 'repeat', and 'for'. The command 'continue' inside
			an iteration code block tells to stop the current iteration
			immediately and start the next iteration. The command 'break'
			stops all iterations immediately and the commands after an
			iteration process are executed.
		</para>
	</sect1>
	
	
	<sect1>
		<title>SPARK-PL basic types</title>
		<sect2>
		<title>number</title>
		<para>
			The most basic type is 'number' (or 'double'). This type
			represents a numerical value. It corresponds to a double
			type in many other programming languages. So it can be used
			for representing both integers and floating point numbers.
		</para>
		<para>
			By default, all numerical variables are initialized with 0.
			All usual arithmetical operations are available for numbers:
			+, - (binary and unary), *, /. 
			The operator '%' finds a residual of a division.
			The operator '^' raises its left hand side to the power
			from the right hand size.
			There are several operators which combines the assignment with
			an arithmetic operation: +=, -=, *=, /=. These operators are
			explained in the following example.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
var x = 20
var y = 30

; Equivalent to
; x = x + 1
x += 1

; Equivalent to
; x = x * y
x *= y
</programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			There are all usual mathematical functions in SPARK-PL like
			'sin', 'cos', 'exp'. Commands 'floor', 'ceil', and 'round' are
			used for rounding a number (see SPARK-PL dictionary for
			a full description). The command 'random a' returns a random number uniformly
			distributed in the interval [0,a) (the returned value is always less than a). 
			The command 'random-in-interval a b' returns a uniformly distributed
			random number in the interval [a, b).
		</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
		<title>boolean</title>
		<para>
			The next basic type is 'boolean' (or 'bool'). This is a logical
			type. Variables of this type have two values: true or false.
			The default value is false. Operators for boolean
			values are: 'and', 'or', 'not'. The meaning of these operators
			should be clear. There are several comparison operators for numbers
			which yield a boolean result: &lt;, &gt;, &lt;=, &gt;=,
			==, !=. The last two operators mean equality and inequality
			respectively. Logic operators are often used in 'if'
			command for combining different conditions.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
if (x &gt; 30 and x &lt; 100) or y == 1
[
	do-something x
]
</programlisting>
		</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
		<title>string</title>
		<para>
			Strings in SPARK-PL are represented by the 'string' type.
			Constants of this type should be always
			written inside double quotes. There is a concatenation operation
			for strings represented by the '+' operator. Note: operations and functions
			in SPARK-PL can be overloaded. It means that the same operator or the same
			function name can correspond to several actual functions. The right function
			is choosen based on the types of arguments. An example of a command
			taking a string argument is 'print'. This command prints out its argument
			in the standard output stream. Also this command can be used
			with numerical arguments to print out numbers (or with
			other types to print out information about that types).
<programlisting language="SPARK">
to do-something [x]
	var str1 = "hello,"
	var str2 = " world"
	print str1 + str2
	print x
end
</programlisting> 
		</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
		<title>vector</title>
		<para>
			The next type is 'vector'. It is more advanced type representing
			a 3-d (or 2-d) vector. The constants of this type has the form
			'[a, b, c]' where a, b, c are some numerical constants (in the
			current SPARK-PL implementation it is not allowed to have variables
			inside vector constants). There is a command 'create-vector'
			with three arguments which creates a new vector with the given
			entries. For this command any arguments can be used. Also, vectors
			has all usual arithmetic operations: +, - for vectors, * for
			a vector and a number, / for a vector on the left and a number on
			the right. Also shortcuts +=, -=, *=, /= work for vectors (last
			two operators expect numbers on the right hand side). It is also
			possible to compare two vectors using '==' and '!=' operators.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
; All vectors initialized by a zero vector by default
var v1 : vector
var v2 = [1, 2, 3.3]

; v1 = [3, 6, 9.9]
v1 = v2 * 3
v2 -= v1 + v2 * 4

var v3 = create-vector v1.x (v2.y + 3) v1.y
</programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			The vector type has special methods. The method 'length' returns
			the length of a vector. The method 'normalize' normalizes a
			vector (makes it of the unit length) and returns the result
			of the normalization (it modifies the vector which called
			'normalize' and returns a reference to the same vector after modification).
			There are three fields in each vector: 'x', 'y', 'z' which
			represent the corresponding vector entries.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
; After the normalization we get v1 == v2
v2 = v1.normalize

; Due to numerical errors it cannot be guaranteed that
; v1.length == 1 exactly
v2.x = v1.length
</programlisting>
		</para>
		</sect2>
		<sect2>
		<title>Arrays and lists</title>
		<para>
			All basic types discussed so far were primitive SPARK-PL types.
			Besides primitive types there are composite types. The most important
			composite types are arrays and lists. In SPARK-PL it is often
			not important whether a given object has an array or a list type
			because there are commands which work with both types in the same way.
			In general, lists are more flexible, meanwhile arrays
			are more efficient. These types are used for storing several
			objects of another type in the same variable. To declare a variable
			which has a list type, use the following syntax
<programlisting language="SPARK">
class TestClass

; A list of vectors
var x : List&lt;vector&gt;

; An array of strings
var strings : Array&lt;string&gt;

; A list of TestClass objects
var tests : List&lt;TestClass&gt;
</programlisting>
			Due to limitations of the current version of SPARK-PL, it is not possible
			to use 'number' and 'bool' as a subtype of composite types. Also,
			composite types cannot be used as arguments of other composite types.
			If you need a list of numbers, then there are two simple solutions.
			One is to create a list of vectors and then use only one component of
			each vector. Another solution is to create a custom class 'NumberClass' with
			one numeric field and use this class as the argument of composite types.
			The same trick works for creating composite types which include other
			composite types.
		</para>
		<para> 
			The command	'count' returns the number of objects inside a list or an array.
			The command 'create' creates an array of objects. This command
			has two arguments: a type name of objects to be created and a
			number of objects in the new array. This operation cannot be used for numbers
			and boolean values. All objects in a created array are initialized by their default
			values. To get a particular element of an array (or a list)
			use the 'get' command. It has two arguments: an array or a list and
			the index of an element there (indices start from 0). Lists are created with
			the command 'create-list' which has one argument: a name of the subtype. Elements
			can be added to a list with 'add' command, removed from a list with 'remove' command.
			See the dictionary for all available list and array commands.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
; Creates an array with 100 vectors
var array = create vector 100

; Get the 4-th element in the array
var v = get array 3

; Create a list of strings
var list = create-list string

; Add several strings to the list
list.add "first"
list.add "second"

; Remove an element from the list
list.remove "first"

; Prints "second"
print (get list 0)
</programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			The most useful command which can be used with arrays
			and lists is the 'ask' command. This command does several
			things. To understand it completely, first look at another
			application of the 'ask' command. It can be used with
			any object (not with a number or a boolean value) as its argument.
			When a method is executed there is always one implicit variable
			named 'self'. This variable refers to an object for which the method
			is executed. Very often it is used implicitly.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
class SomeClass

to method1
end

to method2
	; The next command will be translated as
	; self.method1
	; that is, the method 'method1' is called
	; for the current active object.
	method1
end
</programlisting>
			This 'self' variable can be always used explicitly.
			The command 'ask' with an object argument temporary changes
			this 'self' reference to its argument.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
to method
	var v : vector

	v.x = 1
	v.y = 2
	v.z = 3
	
	; The same things in another way
	ask v
	[
		; Inside this block 'self' reference is set
		; to the vector 'v', so its fields x, y, z
		; can be accessed directly without
		; an explicit reference to the object 'v'.
		x = 1
		y = 2
		z = 3
	]
end
</programlisting>
			Now it is easy to explain the effect of the 'ask' command
			applied to an array (or a list). First of all, it iterates
			through all objects inside an array, and during each iteration
			it assigns the 'self' reference to the current object in 
			the array and performs all commands inside the code block
			for that object.
<programlisting language="SPARK">
to method
	var array = create vector 100
	
	var i = 0
	
	ask array
	[
		x = i
		y = 2 * i
		z = 3 * i

		i += 1
	]
end
</programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			Sometimes it is required to refer to an object which started
			the 'ask' command inside the 'ask' command block (remember
			that inside that block the 'self' reference is different).
			In order to do so, use 'myself' reference. This reference
			always refers to an object which started the 'ask' command.
			Furthermore, 'ask' commands can be nested in each other.
			There is also the reference 'this' which returns a reference
			to the object for which the current method is executed.
			Another reference is 'parent' which returns a reference
			to the parent object of 'this'. The main purpose of
			the 'parent' reference is to call a parent class method that has the same
			name as a method in a child class from the child class.
<programlisting language = "SPARK">
class Parent

var x : number

to function
end

class Child : Parent

var x : vector

to function
	parent.function
	
	ask create vector 100
	[
		; This refers to vector's x component
		x = 2
		
		; This refers to a variable x defined in Child
		myself.x = [1, 2, 3]
		
		; This refers to a variable x defined in Parent
		parent.x = 2
		
		; myself.x is a vector
		ask myself.x
		[
			; Now myself refers to a vector
			; from the previous 'ask' code block
			myself.x = 1
			
			; Again we refer to Child.x
			this.x = [3, 4, 5]
		]
	]
end
</programlisting>
		</para>
		<para>
			The last note is about visibility of variables inside 'ask' blocks. All local variables
			are visible inside 'ask' blocks. If there is a field in the object referred by 'self'
			with the same name as a local variable, then the local variable always shadows the
			field with the same name. Here is an example:
<programlisting language = "SPARK">
to some-method
	var x = 1
	var v : vector
	v.x = 2
	
	ask v
	[
		; Prints 1  
		print x
		
		; Prints 2
		print self.x
	]
end
</programlisting>
		</para>
		</sect2>
	</sect1>
</article>