<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V5.0//EN" "../DocBook/docbook-5.0/dtd/docbook.dtd">
<article>
	<info>
		<title> SPARK: creating the first model with Eclipse (Gary An's Toy
			Infection Model)
	</title>
		<author>
			<personname>
				Alexey Solovyev
	</personname>
		</author>
	</info>

	<section>
		<title>Installing Eclipse</title>
		<para>Before you start the development of the first model using
			SPARK you need to
			obtain good tools. All SPARK models are written in
			Java programming language. So
			the first step before doing anything in
			SPARK is to learn this programming
			language. Probably, this is the
			main drawback of SPARK (especially compared to
			NetLogo) since the
			process of learning Java is not the simplest one. But if you are
			already familiar with this language or know other object oriented
			languages
			such as C++ or C#, then studying basics of Java will be very
			easy (I think that among
			triple C++, Java, C#, the Java language is
			the easiest one to learn, though not the
			easiest one to program on).
			All Java-related information can be found on the
			site:
			[url/]
			Particullary easy and basic tutorials on Java are:
			[url/] [Here is one
			good news: I will try to present everything in the manner which
			will
			not involve any knowledge in Java or OOP. I shall cover the creationg
			of the
			model in SPARK step by step with detailed explanations. If you
			just repeat all my
			steps then at least you will create the SPARK model
			and also along the way you learn
			some basic concepts of Java.] 
		</para>
		<para> It is possible to write any Java program just using the Notepad
			in Windows. But
			nobody will do this. Instead it is much more
			convenient to work with specially
			designated tools for writing Java
			programs. One of the most popular tools, or
			IDE, for Java is called
			Eclipse which is developed by the IBM corporation. The
			main advantage
			of this IDE is that it is completely free. So let's download and
			install it. Go to the site
			[url/], choose the following Eclipse
			version: [eclipse], download it. Now
			follow installation instructions
			to complete Eclipse setup process. It worth
			to mention that you don't
			need Java to be installed on your computer to be able to
			run Eclipse
			and write Java programs in it: everything is already included in the
			Eclipse distributive [verify this] 
		</para>

	</section>

	<section>
		<title>General description of the biological model</title>
		<para> Before we continue with programming let's first decide what we
			want to
			program. Of course, we want to create a biological model in
			the SPARK. Moreover,
			we already have in mind one particular model: Toy
			Infection Model by Dr. Gary An
			[reference]. So let study this model
			closer. This model is a model of
			inflammation, the response of the
			immune system on the infection.
			[blah-blah-blah] 
			</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Main components: agents, space, data layers
		</title>
		<para> Let me introduce the main concepts of SPARK. They are agents,
			spaces, and data
			layers. First of all agents. The simplest way to
			think about an agent is that it is
			something that can move around and
			do some work. The key word here is 'do'.
			Actually, agents can be
			immobile of they even can be invisible entities. But the
			main thing
			about agents is that they can do something. What they can do exactly
			is
			determined by the rules and by the modeler. The main purpose of ABM
			is to use simple
			rules for individual agents which result in complex
			global system behavior. In
			SPARK are by default should do some work
			each simulation step. There are two main
			types of agents in SPARK:
			those who can be visualized, or, more precisely, are
			allowed to
			'physically' interact with other agents (the meaning of this will be
			clear later when I describe what is the space), and those who are
			'invisible' and
			do some supplementary work. To make the concept of
			agent interaction more clear
			let's consider an example. Human beings
			can be treated as completely isolated
			entities, things in themselves,
			if we consider someone's mind. We cannot say
			what other people are
			thinking and what they want if they do not tell us it
			directly.
			Moreover, people cannot share thoughts without some mediators like
			speech (hearing), gestures (sight), etc. The same can be said about
			agents in
			SPARK: other agents are not aware about the internal state
			of the given agent. But
			as humans, agents can communicate with each
			other and share information. And
			again as humans they do not
			communicate absolutely directly but use some
			mediators. In SPARK the
			main 'mediator' is the space, the space where agents
			exist and where
			they can 'meet' other agents and 'talk' with them. We see another
			aspect of the space: not just a mediator, but also a place where
			agents exist (not
			very accurately, because one can argue that agents
			exist in the computer
			memory). And it makes sense that the mediator
			related to the place of existence.
			Indeed, consider you want to be
			heard by everyone on the Earth. What can you do?
			Shout as loud as you
			can will not be successful since people in Australia will for
			sure not
			hear you if you are in Russia. Of course, you can use some modern
			communication devices but still there will be people who will not
			hear you in
			spite of all your efforts. Why? Because they are too far
			away from you. The same is
			true for agents in the space: they cannot
			communicate directly with all other
			agents at once because distinct
			agents occupy different space positions and
			some agents can be too far
			away from each other to be involved in any sort of
			interaction. </para>
		<para> To sun up, I just repeat: agents are entities that can do some
			work according to
			well defined (by the modeler) rules. The space is
			the place where agents exist and
			through which they can interact with
			other agents. In biology the analogue of an
			agent is a cell and the
			analogue of the space is the space surrounding cells.
			</para>
		<para> The third concept is the data layers. To introduce it, I think
			the biological
			interpretation will be good. Besides cells (agents)
			each biological system
			involve many chemical compounds, consisting of
			different types of molecules.
			It is possible to think (and model)
			molecules (and therefore chemical
			compounds) as agents. But let's
			think about this. In one mole there are
			approximately [Avogadro]
			molecules. It's a huge number. Even if in the modeled
			system you are
			dealing with smaller amounts of chemicals, still the number of
			molecules is overwhelming, and it is physically impossible for modern
			computers to work with such large number of idependent entites,
			agents. So
			somehow we need to represent all chemistry in other way.
			And the simplest way is to
			work not with individual molecules but with
			many of them at once. We can achieve
			this by defining the
			concentration of a chemical compound at each point of the
			space. So
			the problem now is how to define this concentration. From
			mathematical
			point of view the concentration is just a number which is
			assigned to each point in
			the space, so it is a function which takes
			as arguments coordinates of a space
			point and returns one number: a
			concentration of a chemical compound. And in
			SPARK such functions are
			called data layers. The simplest way to implement a data
			layer is the
			following. Assume that we have a continuous space and want to define
			a
			data layer for it. Divide the bounded region of the space into cells
			and assign to
			each point inside the same cell the same value. Then we
			get a grid atop the space
			which associate some numerical values to
			each point of the space. This is so
			called grid data layer. </para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Creating the model project in Eclipse</title>
		<para>
			Start Eclipse first. Now
			choose Java perspective. [how to do
			this?] Now we may return to pure
			programming
			things. To create our
			model in Eclipse we first need to create a Java
			project in
			Eclipse.
			Here are the steps of this procedure: [steps] Now your screen should
			look
			like the following.
			[picture/] But this new project is just a
			general Java application not related
			in any
			sense to the SPARK. To
			provide such a relation you need to specify that
			your project
			works
			with the SPARK. Right click on the project name and choose
			[configure
			building
			path, etc.] Click save icon [to save project?] Now we create
			the run
			configuration to
			be able to run and test our model directly
			from Eclipse. [choose run
			as... and
			configure all including working
			directory [should be Release\] and main class,
			TODO:work with SPARK to
			make it understand command line and
			immediately open models]
			In command
			line arguments we specified file called model.xml. Right now
			this file
			does not exist in our project but shortly we will create it. This
			file
			describes
			everything contained in our model and it is used by
			SPARK GUI to find the
			actual files of
			our model components. [package
			creation]
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Creating agent classes</title>
		<para> First of all let's create all agents for our Toy Infection
			Model. Right now, we
			will not write any code but just create classes.
			Right click on the name of the
			project in the Navigator panel on the
			src folder. Choose New -> Class. [etc.]
			</para>
		<para> We need to create three agents: Basic Agent (BasicAgent class),
			Infection
			Agent (InfectAgent class), Iflammatory Cell (IflamCell
			class). First create
			BasicAgent class. After the file is created, open
			it (if it is not open yet) and add
			the following lines right after the
			package definition: import static
			org.spark.utils.RandomHelper.nextDoubleFromTo; import
			org.spark.space.SpaceAgent; import org.spark.utils.Vector; These
			lines
			just tell to import some functions from other packages. Next
			modify the class
			declaration line: add the following words: after
			public class BasicAgents add
			extends SpaceAgent This means that
			BasicAgent class inherits all
			functionality from the SpaceAgent class.
			The Space agent is the most common type
			of agents: all agents which
			can be visualized and are able to interact with other
			agents should be
			defined as Space agents. Space agents can be mobile or static.
			The
			last thing to do with the BasicAgent class is to add the following
			lines inside
			class itself: [code, insert here, not later since it is a
			supplementary class]
			[in two other classes insert dummy step method,
			the code will be provided in the
			later sections] [Step method is
			called every tick, or every step of the model
			execution process.]
		</para>

		<para> The role of each agent will be clear later. Now I just mention
			that there are
			actually only two types of agents: inflammatory cells
			and infection agents. The
			purpose of the Basic Agent is just to
			provide the functionality shared by both
			types of agents. In terms of
			OOP it is just the common parent of two main agent
			classes. </para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Creating the model setup class</title>
		<para> Now we create another class called Model. This class includes
			the defintions
			of various things of the model. It includes definition
			of global variables and
			model parameters as well as the model setup
			method. The setup method is called
			every time before model can be
			executed. The main purpose of this method is to
			create all objects of
			the model and initialize all variables. We will write the
			setup code
			later. </para>
		<para> Another important thing implemented in the Model class is the
			definition of
			model parameters. [etc] </para>
		<para> The last thing to mention are two methods called begin() and
			end(). The first
			method is invoked each step before processing agent's
			step() methods, and the
			end() method is invoked after all agents were
			processed. This methods are
			convenient for implementing collection of
			statistical data and for performing
			global operations on data layers
			like diffusion. </para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title> Writing xml-model file
		</title>
		<para> It is not sufficient to have Java files created above to create
			a SPARK model.
			The last required file is a file which puts everything
			together. It is not a Java
			file but it is an xml-file. You can call
			this file as you wish but exactly this file
			can be opened from SPARK
			GUI and in this sense the name of this file should be
			associated with
			the name of the model itself. So let's create an xml-file called
			ToyInfectionModel.xml. Right click on the root project folder
			(project name)
			and choose new [etc].
			</para>
		<para>
			Add the following lines in the file:

			<programlisting language="xml">			
	   <![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<model>
	<classpath path="/bin/"/>
	<setup>ToyInfectionModel.Model</setup>
	<mainframe height="675" width="650" x="0" y="0"/>
			
	<agent>ToyInfectionModel.InflamCell</agent>
	<agent>ToyInfectionModel.InfectAgent</agent>
			
</model>
		]]>
			</programlisting>
			This is a minimal working description of the model. The first line is
			just a
			specification of some xml-related stuff. The root element of
			the xml-file is
			called model. Then we define a path to the compiled
			binary files of our model. Next
			we say how the main Model class of our
			model is called and in which package it can be
			found. Then we specify
			parameters of the main window and at two last lines declare
			two agent
			types (classes) in our model [strictly speaking these two lines are
			not
			necessary?]
		</para>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title> Implementing the agent's code</title>
		<para>
			It's time to begin writing the main model code. We have already
			done all
			supporting
			job and can concentrate on the model and its rules.
			First of all let's
			implement
			all rules of agents. We start from the
			Infection Agents.

			[etc]
			[Code and the complete description of it]
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Implementing setup code</title>
		<para>
			We still need to create agents before they will be able to do
			anything.
			All initialization is done inside the setup() method of the
			Model class.
			Here is the code of this method:

			[code]

			Several first lines
			are particularly important and should be present in
			every Spark model.
			What we are doing there is the creation of the
			space.
			The space is not
			created automatically because there are
			different kinds
			of spaces and
			you need to choose which space is the
			best for your model.

			[Standard
			space and NetLogo space]

			[Some words about Observer and its role]

			[end() method code and explanation] 
		</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Adding new render and charts</title>
		<para></para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Adding parameters</title>
		<para></para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Adding data sets</title>
		<para></para>
	</section>
</article>